<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-10-06T00:17:44+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Hamish Edward Teagle - PhD Particle Physics</title><subtitle>My personal page for scientific work, projects, ML and AI, and anything I find interesting!</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Arguably one of the greatest moments in English footballing history..but long forgotten.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/1066/05/01/welcome-to-jekyll.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Arguably one of the greatest moments in English footballing history..but long forgotten." /><published>1066-05-01T11:09:11+01:00</published><updated>1066-05-01T11:09:11+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/1066/05/01/welcome-to-jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/1066/05/01/welcome-to-jekyll.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/NM_goal.png&quot; alt=&quot;The great moment captured&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The great moment is captured in this photo, arguably one of the most impressive feates of individual skill ever seen on the football pitch. Mandela was playing for Shitterton Wanderers FC (on a 2 season loan from Wetwang United) and had taken the team to promotion in the previous season with clean sheets in every game, under management of Zinedine Zidane who was early in his managerial career. Shitterton were in troubling times late in the season, staring into the jaws of relagation, and were struggling against a fresh Brown Willy City side in a scrappy rainy Tuesday relagation battle. The score was 1-1, a win would see either team lifted out of the relagation zone and into safety for the last week of the season. In the 90th minute a corner resulted from a fast break for the Browns, everything was thrown at a last-ditch attempt to win, and the decision was made to bring goal keeper Brad Friedel up for the attack… As the corner was swung, a strong stoke wind took it towards Mandela’s goal and he leaped at the chance for what seemed to be an easy clearence. In actuality, Mandela had planned the move since Friedel left his area to join the attack. And as he leaped he swung into ‘the scorpian’ and clared the ball all the way into the Browns goal, leaving Friedel with no opportunity to scamble back into position.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry></feed>